Shichao Xu

Ph.D. Candidate
Department of Computer Science
Northwestern University
Tech Room L476, 2145 Sheridan Road
Evanston, IL 60208, United States

OBJECTIVE

I am a fourth year Ph.D. candidate and aiming at finding a full-time research/engineering intern position.

E-mail: shichaoxu2023@u.northwestern.edu

Homepage: https://shichao.netlify.app

Linkedin: linkedin.com/in/shichao-xu-6a0584214

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Machine/Deep learning, Learning from imperfect data, Computer Vision, Reinforcement learning

SUMMARY

I am a fourth-year Ph.D. candidate in the Computer Science Department at Northwestern University, and my advisor is Prof Qi Zhu. I also work collaboratively with Prof. Xiao Wang, Prof. Zhaoran Wang from Northwestern University, Prof. Yanzhi Wang from Northeastern University, Prof. Zheng O'Neill from Texas A&M University. I received my undergraduate degree from Shanghai Jiao Tong University (ACM Honors Class) in 2018. Previously, I was a research intern in visual computing group at MSRA, under the supervision of Jifeng Dai. I also worked as a research assistant at SJTU BCMI Lab, directed by Prof. Liqing Zhang.

My research interests lie in the field of **Artificial Intelligence** and **Cyber-Physical System**, especially with the topic of **learning from imperfect data**. While deep learning is more and more frequently included as a component of a large complex system with various factors included, many challenges are exposed in actual development and integration. Instead of simply considering AI as a stand-alone software application, we should take more issues into account – **data availability and quality, disturbance and attacks**, **generalization and adaptation**, etc. And one of our latest works Weak Adaptation Learning which relates to data availability and quality is accepted by ICCV 2021. And our paper Non-Transferable Learning which related to generalization and adaptation also gets a high score (8/8/8) in ICLR 2022.

EDUCATION BACKGROUND

Northwestern University
Ph.D. in Computer Science (GPA: 3.9/4.0)
Master's degree in Computer Science (GPA: 3.9/4.0)

Cornell University
Summer School

ACM Class, Zhiyuan College, Shanghai Jiao Tong University
Bachelor of Science in Computer Science (GPA 3.9/4.3)

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science (GPA 3.9/4.3)

IL, USA
09/2018-06/2023(expected)
09/2018-06/2021

NY, USA
Shanghai, China
09/2014-07/2018

RESEARCH EXPERIENCES

Northwestern University
Research Assistant in IDEAS Lab

Shanghai Jiao Tong University
Research Assistant in Center for Brain-like Computing and Machine Intelligence

09/2014-07/2018

Research Intern in Visual Computing Group

08/2017-01/2018

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- Fu Yangyang, Shichao Xu, Qi Zhu, and Zheng O'Neill. "Containerized Framework for Building Control Performance Comparisons: Model Predictive Control vs Deep Reinforcement Learning Control." (2021). The 8th ACM International Conference on Systems for Energy-Efficient Buildings, Cities, and Transportation (BuildSys '21), 2021
- Lixu Wang*, Shichao Xu*, Ruiqi Xu, Xiao Wang, and Qi Zhu. "Non-Transferable Learning: A New Approach for Model Verification and Authorization." (latest! ICLR 2022, score 8/8/8, currently ranked 15th among all.)
- Shichao Xu, Yangyang Fu, Yixuan Wang, Zheng O'Neill, and Qi Zhu. "Model-assisted Learning-based Framework for Sensor Fault-Tolerant Building HVAC Control." The 8th ACM International Conference on Systems for Energy-Efficient Buildings, Cities, and Transportation (BuildSys '21), 2021, Coimbra, Portugal (acceptance ratio = 26%)
- Shichao Xu*, Lixu Wang*, Yixuan Wang, and Qi Zhu. "Weak Adaptation Learning--Addressing Cross-domain Data Insufficiency with Weak Annotator." IEEE/CVF International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV) 2021.
- Lixu Wang, Shichao Xu, Xiao Wang, and Qi Zhu. "Towards Class Imbalance in Federated Learning." In 35th
 Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), A Virtual Conference, 2021.
- Qi Zhu, Chao Huang, Ruochen Jiao, Shuyue Lan, Hengyi Liang, Xiangguo Liu, Yixuan Wang, Zhilu Wang, Shichao Xu "Safety-Assured Design and Adaptation of Learning-Enabled Autonomous Systems." Proceedings of the 26th Asia and South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASP-DAC). 2021.
- Yixuan Wang, Chao Huang, Zhilu Wang, Shichao Xu, Zhaoran Wang, Qi Zhu. "Cocktail: Learn a Better Neural Network Controller from Multiple Experts via Adaptive Mixing and Robust Distillation" 2021 58th ACM/IEEE Design Automation Conference (DAC), Virtual Conference, 2021.
- Rumia Masburah, Rajib Lochan Jana, Ainuddin Khan, Shichao Xu, Shuyue Lan, Soumyajit Dey, Qi Zhu, "Adaptive Learning Based Building Load Prediction for Microgrid Economic Dispatch" Design, Automation & Test in Europe Conference & Exhibition (DATE), 2021
- Shichao Xu, Yixuan Wang, Yanzhi Wang, Zheng O'Neill, and Qi Zhu. "One for Many: Transfer Learning for Building HVAC Control." In Proceedings of the 7th ACM International Conference on Systems for Energy-Efficient Buildings, Cities, and Transportation, (BuildSys '20), 2020.
- Shichao Xu, Shuyue Lan, and Zhu Qi, "MaskPlus: Improving Mask Generation for Instance Segmentation" The IEEE
 Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV). 2020
- Chao Huang, Shichao Xu, Zhilu Wang, Shuyue Lan, Wenchao Li, and Qi Zhu. "Opportunistic Intermittent Control with Safety Guarantees for Autonomous Systems," 2020 57th ACM/IEEE Design Automation Conference (DAC), San Francisco, CA, USA, 2020, pp. 1-6

Skill/Tools

Python(experienced), C/C++(experienced), Pytorch(experienced), Tensorflow(experienced for ver<2.0), Algorithm(experienced), Latex(experienced), Docker(intermediate), Html(intermediate), Git(intermediate).

PROJECT

DoE Project: <u>Securing Grid-interactive Efficient Buildings (GEB) through Cyber Defense and Resilient System (CYDRES).</u>

<u>AWARDS</u>

D . CO.O.1 T.

•	DAC2021 Young Fellows program	2021
•	Northwestern University Ph.D. Fellowship	2018-2019
•	Zhiyuan College honor scholarship	2014-2018
•	Excellent students' scholarship, Shanghai Jiao Tong University	2014-2018
•	Bronze medal in National Olympiad in Informatics	2013
•	Gold medal in National Olympiad in Informatics in Provinces	2012